What if the 1959 kitchen debates between the vice president of the United States, Richard
Nixon, and the head of Russia, Nikita Khrushchev, weren't about communism and capitalism at
all? But instead, what if that moment was the crossroad between videotape, vodka, and
Pepsi? Well, it certainly was.
The story you're about to hear has never been told before. You're listening to the 82nd
episode of Tracing the Path, a podcast that connects the most important people, places,
and events of the 20th century in ways you never could have imagined. I'm your host,
Dan R. Morris. Welcome.
Throughout the history of the world, the United States and Russia have been enemies
only once. And to add to that, they weren't even military adversaries. They were ideological
foes. That period existed from 1944 to 1991, and has had somewhat of resurgence since
2022. Otherwise, they have remained neutral acquaintances, and sometimes military allies.
Historically, the relationship began in 1763, when American merchants docked in St. Petersburg
in hopes of trading their wares. Having been to the West Indies, American ships were carrying
sugar, indigo, tobacco, rum, rice, mahogany, and sassafras. And in return, they left with
flax canvas, hemp, iron, and fur. For Catherine the Great, America's revolution
to break away from the British crown wasn't ideal. She was not interested in backing a
revolt. But America would be a new trading partner. Plus, as long as Great Britain was
tied up with America, it posed less of a threat to Russia. Except for the part where Great
Britain caused great problems for commercial boats looking to trade.
Thus, while she didn't publicly support America, Catherine the Great also turned down Great
Britain when they asked if they could borrow 20,000 troops to help get the Americans back
in line. The situation was similar a hundred years later,
in 1863, when the US was involved in its own civil war. Then, Czar Alexander II was head
of Russia. He also didn't publicly support Abraham Lincoln's Union. But when Great Britain
and France were starting to discuss the possibility of recognizing the Southern Confederacy, Russia
sent navy ships to New York and San Francisco as a gesture of goodwill. But perhaps also
a kind of show of strength. Russia's adversarial relationship with Great
Britain created another opportunity for America. With the feeling that they wouldn't be able
to properly defend their territory of Alaska, since it was right next to Britain's Canada,
they sold Alaska to the United States. For most of the time, US and Russia relations
were fine. By 1890, companies like Singer Sewing Machines, Westinghouse, and MetLife
all had subsidiaries in Russia and were doing business. The only real reason any trading
would stop would be by the natural advancements that came over time. For instance, the trade
for hemp with Russia was strong until manila rope became a viable alternative. And flax
canvas remained a strong trading product until cotton in the US south began to dominate.
And importing iron for Russia became too expensive once the US canal and railroad options had
been completed. By 1912, Singer Sewing Machines alone had 30-40,000 employees in Russia. It
had hundreds of retail locations and factories, so much so that Russians called any sewing
machine a Singer. The Russian ruble, which was tied to the gold standard, was one of
Europe's strongest currencies. But when World War I rolled around in 1914,
everything started to change, because Russia needed its gold to finance the war, and thus
it took the ruble off the gold standard. And then after the war in a somewhat shattered
place when rest and rebuilding was required, that is when Lenin and the Bolsheviks began
their revolution, leading to the reign of Vladimir Lenin.
Lenin's view of the world changed Russia's relationship with the world completely. He
believed private ownership of industry should end, and should be the business of the state.
So overnight, Singer Sewing Machines lost its factories, Westinghouse lost its investment,
and MetLife lost everything they had. That would be the end of foreign products in
Russia. At that point, pretty much everything had come
under state control. Alcohol, for instance, had already been under state control when
they passed that law in 1896. But when Lenin took over, the alcohol industry
had been shut down. A dry law had been passed right before World War I to make sure their
soldiers were not inebriated before going to war, and to make sure they could make Molotov
cocktails with the factories that produced vodka.
But after the war, Lenin reopened the alcohol industry and built a massive Moscow State
warehouse that employed 1500 people and produced 26 million liters of vodka in his first year.
The vodka it produced and delivered to the Kremlin was called the vodka of the capital,
or rather in Russian it was called Stolichnaya. One of the side effects of pushing out foreign
companies from inside of Russia was the new cultural gap that would begin to form, where
no news left Russia and no news entered Russia. Even companies like Pathé, which was France's
largest filmmaker, they had theaters in Russia. But after Lenin took over, there were no new
foreign films being shown. For the rest of Europe, Pathé theaters were
more than just theaters. They were in fact the place that Europe got its news.
It was back in 1909 when Pathé was already operating over 200 theaters in Europe, and
they felt they had a real chance to be more important than just a movie theater. They
actually began to cobble together images, film footage, and text to create 7 to 10 minutes
of news items that would be projected before a movie would start. They would be called
newsreels. Newsreels were important for two reasons.
One, it might be the only place someone could see film footage of a world event. But two,
for theaters, who found it important to get people to come back to the theater every week,
found it difficult to keep people coming back when the movie didn't change. But once newsreels
were added, twice a week, there would be something new to see.
In the United States, it wasn't until 1929, at the beginning of the Great Depression,
that Universal started doing the same thing, providing newsreels twice a week before the
movies in their theaters. And until 1952, with the advent of television, the newsreels
at the cinema were the only moving images people would ever see of major events.
Consider Charles Lindbergh's 1927 flight, or the attack on Pearl Harbor, or the bullet
reel car of Bonnie and Clyde. The world certainly heard about the events on the radio and read
them in the paper. But the newsreel before the movie was film footage.
In thinking through who were the most important storytellers of the 20th century, the newsreel
producers should probably top that list. That is, until the day they became irrelevant.
For Russia, however, the story was a little different. Their state-run newsreel service
was called Kinokronika. They were the most important storytellers from the government's
point of view, as they were only allowed to produce government-approved stories about
things like agriculture, or new factory openings, or new speeches.
Which brings us to the next hero of our story, straight from the heart of Central Russia.
It was 1892 when Alexander M. Poniatoff was born in Russkaya Aysha, an area of Central
Russia. As a child, he loved trains and dreamed of
one day being an engineer. Early on, his father saw in him some engineering talent, and sent
him to a technical school in Germany to study. This was, of course, prior to World War I,
when Russia was part of the world economy. Unfortunately, Alexander was unaware of the
tension that existed between Germany and Russia, and so he was still in Germany when World
War I started. And being from the enemy's home country, he was forced to flee to Belgium
and didn't make it home until 1916. There he enlisted in the army, trying to become
a pilot, but the end of the war was near and he ended up getting stuck at home.
Immediately after the war, as noted, the Russian Revolution began, with Lenin overthrowing
the government. So to evade the chaos completely, Alexander fled to China and found work with
Sheng-Hao Power. And then, in 1927, a few years later, he made one more jump to the United States.
After three years of solid work in New York, where he was able to acquire two patents for
his work, Alexander decided he wanted to see and live in San Francisco. Thus, his next
adventure would begin. In 1934, he was directed to a gentleman named T. Irving Moseley of
the Dalmo Victor Company. Dalmo specialized in radar systems for planes and submarines.
Alexander was put in charge of developing and testing a thermal control system for them.
But when World War II hit, they needed Alexander's skill focus on developing airborne radar scanners
for the US Navy. The contract they had with the government to create these radar scanners
was only for 100 days. At the end of that, they would need a working prototype. But they
made that agreement before they realized the motors and generators they needed didn't exist.
But they knew Alexander could build them. So they convinced him to start his own company
to build these required motors and generators, because they could pay him much more if he
was a consultant than if he was an employee. So he took his initials, Alexander Matvovich
Poniatoff's initials, A.M.P., and added the word "excellence" to come up with his new company name, Ampex.
The work was steady until the war ended, wherein Alexander needed a new project to work on.
One thing that piqued his interest was the German-invented magnetophone. It was the first
reel-to-reel tape recorder. It was an amazing invention that allowed radio to finally broadcast
taped recordings. Prior to the invention of that, everything on radio was live. Nothing
could be saved and then rebroadcast. For another time, for another time zone, it all had to
be live. So Alexander and his team, including a young Ray Dolby, who would later create
Dolby Labs, set out to make an even better version of this magnetophone. And they decided
to see if they could make one for video as well. Their audio recorder caught the attention
of radio megastar Bing Crosby. He'd heard about it and wanted to see it in action. He
desperately needed this tape recorder. At the time, he wasn't even doing radio, because
he'd become frustrated with all of the regimented work that was required to pull off live recordings.
And he'd already asked if he could play pre-recorded stuff on the radio. But the quality wasn't
there yet, and ABC said no. But this new Ampex tape recorder could change all of that. In
1947, after hearing the Ampex recording, ABC said yes to Bing Crosby. So Bing ordered $50,000
of equipment from Ampex to start recording his own music. That money helped Ampex fund
the work and research it needed to build a video recorder. And that hard work paid off.
On April 14, 1956, at the National Association of TV and Radio Broadcasters, Ampex unveiled
to the world their VR1000 video recorder system, camera, tape, and playback. It was so groundbreaking,
from that event alone, they got 45 orders, at $45,000 each, in 1956. It would be the
first time television could broadcast something that wasn't live. And that moment changed
the world forever. Unfortunately for the important newsreel producers and storytellers, Ampex's
new technology meant newsreels were no longer needed. Now television would broadcast moving film.
But this happening in 1956 brings us to the next hero of our story, Mr. Donald Kendall.
Because in 1956, Mr. Kendall became the Vice President of Marketing at Pepsi Cola. And
while that may seem immediately off base from our discussion about Russia, vodka, and newsreels,
these stories are about to all come together.
In 1956, Pepsi wasn't a new drink. It originated back in 1893 in North Carolina, when Caleb
Bradham invented it, calling it Brad's drink. But one could say marketing had been at the
heart of Pepsi from the very beginning, because it wasn't long before Brad renamed his drink.
He learned that his drink relieved dyspepsia, and thought more people would buy it if it
were called Pepsi Cola. Originally, it was only sold as a syrup for mixing at soda fountains,
but soon after was sold in bottles. As more proof of its early marketing prowess, in 1909,
Pepsi hired Barney Oldfield, one of automobile racing's pioneers, to help market the drink.
But even the best of intentions couldn't prepare for the changes World War I would
create. The fluctuating price of sugar was too much for the young company, and Pepsi
went bankrupt in 1923.
Charles Guth, a candy seller and multi-candy shop owner, decided to buy Pepsi because he
could sell it in his candy stores. With Coca Cola also marketing their drink, this new
Cola flavor was starting to reach everyone, and Guth thought he could double the sales
that Pepsi had ever received.
Seeing Coke was having success pushing every Coke for only a nickel, Guth decided to join
him and sell every Pepsi bulk Cola bottle for a nickel, except Guth decided to sell
12-ounce bottles instead of Coke's 6-ounce bottles.
And so to make this announcement to the world, on the radio he decided to create a jingle
that would illustrate this new difference. And incidentally, this jingle they created
to sell Pepsi became the world's first jingle that would also become a number one hit song.
So much so he even got Duke Ellington and Lionel Hampton to play it at their live events.
When World War II started, sugar was again Pepsi's biggest problem. The government
enacted a sugar rationing program, which meant Pepsi actually had to build a factory in Mexico
to get the sugar it needed to sell Pepsi nationwide.
Coke, on the other hand, negotiated big government contracts to have Coca Cola sent to the troops,
and thus it became exempt from the sugar rationing program. And not only that, the government
helped Coca Cola set up bottling plants near military bases all over the world.
Our hero of this story, Mr. Donald Kendall, was one of those US soldiers being provided
Coca Cola on the battlefield.
Donald served the Navy as a pilot in the Pacific, earning three medals and the Distinguished
Flying Cross before returning home at the end of the war.
Once home in New Rochelle, New York, Kendall joined Pepsi as a delivery driver and salesman,
working up the ranks to finally becoming VP of Marketing in 1956.
Together, Alfred Steele, the president, and Donald Kendall helped Pepsi boom in the 1950s.
They had amassed 700 bottling plants in 70 countries.
But the country they really wanted to be in was the Soviet Union.
Kendall knew the US government helped Coke expand its operations around the globe, and
also knew one of his biggest opportunities was to expand in places that Coke was not.
The Soviet Union had built an actual iron curtain for trade and commerce, and American
companies were not there.
But the first sign that might be changing was in 1953 at the death of Stalin.
Nikita Khrushchev found his way to be the head of the Soviet Union, and the world found
out he wasn't a Stalin clone.
With both Eisenhower newly elected and Khrushchev newly crowned, the peace and trade summits
the world had wanted and Winston Churchill had been requesting was back on the table.
Therefore, the Soviet Union, Great Britain, France, and the United States would finally
meet in Geneva in 1955.
The hope was that a path to peace, cooperation, and trade could finally be forged again.
But by the end of that summit, little had been agreed upon.
That led Eisenhower to suggest that perhaps the four countries could find some cultural
common ground, which they all agreed on and started immediately.
In fact, the musical Porgy and Bess performed in Moscow and Leningrad, and Russia's Moiseyev
Dance Company toured the US.
American doctors were allowed to come and vaccinate 12 million Russian children during
the polio epidemic there, and painters like Jackson Pollock and Edward Hopper were featured
in museums.
The final cultural exchange agreement between the countries, however, didn't get signed
until 1958, and it included exhibitions that each would organize in the other's country.
The US and Russia exhibitions would be in 1959.
Khrushchev felt that hosting the Moscow exhibition would show the world what a true superpower
they were.
And Eisenhower thought if they could be there for the exhibition, it would show Russians
that capitalism and America was ultimately good.
One of the themes the US felt it had to overcome with Russians was the idea that capitalism
led to greed and selfishness.
Khrushchev, back in 1956, had shared his thought that while capitalism is nice, it would die
out long before his country's strong economic position.
He said that they would be around long after capitalism and would be here to bury capitalism.
And his comment, which was translated, "We will bury you," got a lot of press, most
of it out of context.
At home, Eisenhower and the Department of Commerce sent out invitations to 450 American
companies, inviting them to partake in the exhibition and help sponsor the event.
But the Soviet Union was a closed economy, they didn't allow foreign products, and their
currency the ruble, which was not tied to the gold standard, did not have any value
outside of the USSR.
So many of the 450 companies thought it would be a waste of time and money to participate
in such an exhibition.
One of those was Coke, which Donald Kendall thought was a gift, and his first chance at
growing Pepsi in the Soviet Union.
Pepsi, GE, Kodak, IBM, RCA, Sears, and a host of others all were on board for the exhibition.
But for Donald Kendall, the Pepsi board of directors wasn't a hundred percent in alignment
with his plan.
They also thought it was probably not a good use of time and money.
But it was Kendall pushing hard.
He got the approval that he needed, but only because he promised he would personally finance
the entire venture with his own money.
Once approved, he knew something big needed to happen, or he might come back without a
job.
So the night before the Expo, at a VIP dinner, Donald Kendall approached Vice President
Richard Nixon.
He had already met Nixon at some Republican fundraiser dinners, and both of them recognized
each other.
He expressed to Nixon his hope that Nixon help him push Khrushchev to the Pepsi booth
to at least try a free sample.
He would need at least that to satisfy his company.
A picture of Khrushchev drinking Pepsi would be invaluable.
As part of the Expo deal, Pepsi had agreed to send syrup to a local bottling company
to have enough samples for the whole show.
Over three million people were expected to come through the American Exposition.
But Kendall had another plan.
He also brought a Pepsi from home.
And just as requested, while walking together around the Expo Pavilion, Nixon guided Khrushchev
to the Pepsi booth.
And Kendall was ready.
He was ready to appeal to Khrushchev's Russian pride.
He offered Khrushchev a taste test.
In the left hand, Pepsi that was bottled in the United States, and the right hand Pepsi
that was bottled in Moscow.
Khrushchev tried both, and he declared that not only was the drink refreshing, but the
better tasting Pepsi was the one bottled in Moscow.
Pepsi had hit a home run.
But that was not exactly the most memorable moment of that day.
Nixon and Khrushchev had mostly exchanged pleasantries as they walked around the pavilion.
But as they approached the display, showing all the kinds of things that were in American
kitchens, their discussion turned into a heated debate about capitalism versus communism.
And while both felt that they came away looking like they'd won the debate, the world didn't
choose a winner.
They were utterly fascinated by this raw, kitchen debate of two major superpower leaders.
But in the end, it was Khrushchev who could have declared an all-out win in domination.
But unfortunately, he was unaware of a point he could have made unbelievably well.
Fortunately for the world, the kitchen debate had been caught on videotape, something a few
years prior could never have happened.
And it was Nixon who proudly pointed to the film crew from San Francisco's Ampex in touting
the power of this amazing technology.
He promised to Khrushchev the recording would make it around the world and they would not
cut out any of his words.
What Khrushchev never knew was that the videotape recorder technology Nixon was so proud of,
this Ampex out of San Francisco, was the result of Mr. Alexander M. Poniatoff.
This brilliant mind that had ended the newsreel industry and changed the world was in fact
a Russian invention, not an American one.
That probably would have left Nixon speechless.
For Kendall and Pepsi, the door to the Soviet Union was now opened a crack, but it would
take political finesse to close this deal.
Nixon ran for president in 1960 with contributions from Pepsi but ultimately lost.
And afterward, thinking Nixon still had a political future, Kendall moved Pepsi's legal
needs to Nixon's law firm.
The need to maintain that relationship was right on Donald Kendall's part as Nixon
became president in 1968 and some of his first goals were peace and trade talks with Russia.
Nixon asked Henry Kissinger if his team would lobby the Soviet ambassador to allow a trade
delegation to visit with Pepsi's Donald Kendall as the lead.
And the Soviet ambassador agreed.
To break ice at that meeting in Moscow, Kendall brought a transistor radio shaped like a Pepsi
can as a gift.
The smile it created was the opening he needed.
He got the green light to bring Pepsi into Russia.
Except there was one small problem.
Russia was still using the ruble and didn't have any way to pay for it.
So they worked on a barter deal.
Russia could give Pepsi tomato paste, which they could use in all of their Pizza Hut shops
in Europe.
But that wasn't quite enough.
Russia did have one other thing.
They had surplus vodka.
The vodka that was made for the Kremlin, the vodka of the capital, Stolichnaya.
Pepsi would get surplus vodka and the exclusive right to market Stolichnaya vodka in the United
States.
And with the inking of that agreement, Pepsi became the first US consumer good sold in
the Soviet Union.
And Stolichnaya vodka got an American audience.
By 1989, Russians were drinking billions of servings of Pepsi each year.
And Stolichnaya, not as much.
So Pepsi had to renegotiate.
This time the Soviet Union offered Pepsi its outdated military sea craft, 17 submarines,
a cruiser, a frigate, and a destroyer.
And suddenly Pepsi had the sixth largest navy in the world.
They even exclaimed to US Navy Admiral Brent Scowcroft that Pepsi was disarming Russia faster
than the US military.
Of course Pepsi found a buyer of scrap metal in Norway to take the military equipment.
One year later, Russia offered oil tankers and freighters in a $3 billion deal with Pepsi.
But that deal didn't last very long because in 1991, the Soviet Union collapsed and the
country separated into a bunch of independent republics.
The Pepsi bottling it planted up ended up in Belarus.
The Stolichnaya plant ended up in Latvia and the oil tanker manufacturer ended up in Ukraine.
Khrushchev was right, perhaps, in saying the USSR would bury the world in problems.
But the Soviet breakup meant the world's companies would now all be invited to sell
their products back in Russia, like the days of Singer sewing machine.
But this story comes full circle from the days of Lenin and Stalin.
That's because in 1999 Putin came to power with dreams of reviving the Soviet Union to
its former glory.
It started in 2014 by taking the Crimean Peninsula back from Ukraine and then in 2022 by attempting
to take back Ukraine, the biggest of the independent republics.
But instead of closing Russia off from the world from the inside this time, the world
closed Russia off from the outside.
Things like McDonald's, Coke, and even Pepsi ceased producing there.
And in fact the makers of Stolichnaya in Latvia revolted in their own way by getting rid of
the Russian name Stolichnaya and changing it to Stoli, to distance themselves from Russia.
And the calls for a Geneva-like peace meeting have begun again.
But because of the destruction caused by the Ukraine war, this time Russia won't have
any old military equipment to trade to get Pepsi back.
Before we end our tale, let's hear some of the stories they hit the cutting room for.
To start, Pepsi has been on my episode idea list since day one.
I have collected Pepsi cans since 1989 and have collected over 600 cans over the past
40 years and recently turned my collection and my Pepsi can collecting knowledge into
a book.
Look for the Pepsi can collector's almanac anywhere you buy books.
The barter system that Pepsi and Russia went through has existed from the beginning of
time and it is still used today, though most often it's used to get around tariffs and
trade embargoes.
Here are some of the more notable examples of crazy barters.
In 1960, McDonnell Douglas made a deal with Yugoslavia to sell their DC-9 jet and part
of that deal was getting canned ham from Yugoslavia.
In 1970, the Swedish music group ABBA got royalties from sales of music in Russia in
the form of oil commodity shares.
In 1982, New Zealand exchanged lamb for oil with Iran and then in 1985 it traded lamb
to Poland for heavy equipment.
In 1982, America sent dairy products to Jamaica in exchange for the mineral bauxite.
In 1985, Nigeria sent oil to Brazil in exchange for sugar and Volkswagen bugs.
And in 2005, Thailand got F-16 fighter jets from Lockheed, partially exchanged for chickens.
When I was in fifth grade at Elmendorf Air Force Base in Alaska, I got to see Vice President
George Herbert Walker Bush and Admiral Brent Scowcroft speak.
Fortunately, my dad let me leave school that day.
In 1996, Pepsi got Russian astronauts to market Pepsi from the Mir space station.
In 1954, Elvis recorded his first song "That's Alright Mama" on an Ampex tape recorder.
And then in 1955, Ampex got an Oscar for its technical work on the movie musical Oklahoma.
And then in 1957, Ampex won an Emmy for inventing the videotape recorder.
In 1985, Sting recorded the hit song "The Russians" which included Khrushchev's famous
quote, "We will bury you."
Finally, in 1996, Pepsi unveiled a summer program that allowed people to collect Pepsi
points on packaging and then exchange them for Pepsi merchandise.
Well, in one of the TV commercials, a funny moment, a military Harrier jump jet was listed
as one of the prizes you could get if you collected 7 million points.
Nobody really wondered where they got such an idea, but then again, it was only 7 years
after they had one of the biggest navies in the world.
You've been listening to the 82nd episode of "Tracing the Path" with Dan R. Morris.
Search for "Tracing the Path" any place you listen to podcasts and listen in to every
episode.
And many thanks to all the senior center and assisted living communities that use "Tracing
the Path" as their weekly activity hour.